Only one piece of the cloth
陈守杰府中
from Jinxiu Shop
只查到了
at Chen Shoujie's place was found.
一截锦绣坊的布料
I still need to confirm
具体是哪年的图案
which year it's from.
我还得再去确认一下
You're staying out of this?
事不关己
Good.
很好
Jing Lin!
景林
[Yes, Sir.]
是 大阁领
I'll have this madwoman imprisoned
属下这就把这疯妇
in our dungeon right away.
押入内卫府十八层牢狱
Who told you to take her to the IG?
谁说要带回内卫府
Take Lady Yun Que
把云雀姑娘
to the Shen's residence.
带回沈府安置
Lady Yun Que,
云雀姑娘
please.
请吧
[My Lady,]
小姐
[a maid from the Shen's is here.]
沈府的丫鬟求见
He?
小荷
Ma'am,
夫人
please come home and see for yourself.
您快回府看看吧
As soon as Mr Shen left this morning,
大阁领早上一走
[Yun Que became a different person.]
那云雀便换了副模样
We need you. Or things will get outta hand.
您再不管管便要翻天了
Put this ceramic vase
你们把这个瓷瓶
over there.
搬到那边去
Clean
擦一下
[the lantern over there.]
前面的那个灯笼
My Lady, look at her.
夫人 你看她
She's been ordering
全府上下
the whole residence around all day.
都被她折腾半天了
[She mistook someone else for Mr Shen.]
她连大阁领都能认错
[Mr Shen took her in]
大阁领看她可怜
[out of pity.]
好心收留
But she really
她倒好
thinks she's the lady of the house now.
真把自己当主母了
[They need]
还是要跟
[to match the Shen's residence.]
大阁领府的相衬为好
You should go out and see more.
你们还是要多出去看看
[So you'll know better]
这样出去做软垫的时候
[when you go make cushions.]
心中才有数
Have you cleared the grass in the backyard
后院的草清理了吗
[or cleaned the book shelf]
大阁领交代的书架
as asked?
擦了吗
Then what are you waiting for?
那还不赶快去
I asked them to set up the front hall.
我吩咐他们布置前厅
It's not important, huh?
就不算正事了
Lady Yun Que,
云雀姑娘
it's not like that.
您这是哪儿的话
You're being too harsh.
言重了
When you assign tasks to the servants,
您吩咐下人办事
they should naturally do them well.
自然应当办好
However,
可是
Mr Shen will pay us.
我们领的是沈府的银子
We should work for him.
为大阁领办事
I mean,
首先
we must prioritize the tasks
大阁领交代的事情
he's arranged.
我们要先安排好
Don't you think so?
您说是吧
Then I'll do the decorations tomorrow.
那布置的事明日再说
[Sir,]
沈管家
[please sort out the household accounts]
你把府中的账册
[and bring them to me.]
整理整理给我一下
I'll take a look.
我正好看一看
I'm sorry.
抱歉 姑娘
[Only the lady of the house]
沈府的账册
can do that.
只有由府内的主母查看
My Lady,
夫人
good morning.
晨起安康
Sir,
沈管家
why are you...
你今日为何
My Lady,
夫人
I forgot to greet you this morning.
早晨忘了问候夫人
I'm really sorry.
罪该万死
Please punish me.
请夫人责罚
Punish?
责罚
The rules say that
依沈府家规
all the servants
府内家仆
must greet you in the morning and evening.
必然要向夫人晨暮请安
The female members should
女眷也要向夫人
serve tea to you.
施礼敬茶
[Since my first day here,]
我第一天进府中之后
[I've kept this in mind.]
就牢记于心
Rudeness is absolutely intolerable.
沈府不养无礼数之人
I apologize for my disrespect.
今日老奴失礼
Even if you
夫人就是把老奴
kick me out,
逐出府外
I won't have any complaints.
也是名正言顺啊
Enough, enough.
行了行了
[All you want]
说来说去
is for me to serve tea
不就是想让我
to Mrs Shen.
给沈夫人敬茶嘛
I'll just do it.
我敬就是了
Ma'am,
夫人
have some tea.
喝茶
you've had the tea,
现在茶也喝了
and we've been through the rules.
规矩也立得差不多了吧
Let's talk about reasons.
那咱们就来论一论道理
Mr Shen asked me
是大阁领
to oversee the household affairs.
让我管理府中事务的
I naturally need to do my best.
我自然要尽心尽力
Or maybe,
莫非
you wish to go against
夫人想跟大阁领
his decision?
唱反调不成
You just mentioned
云雀姑娘刚刚是说
the accounts, right?
想看账本是吧
Yeah.
对
Since you wanna have a look,
你既然想看
why not
那索性
take it over for the next season as well?
把下一季的账都管了吧
But...
这
[My Lady...]
夫人
You mean
你是说
all the accounts will be managed by me?
所有的账都交给我管
I wasn't very good
我本来对此事
at it anyway.
就不太擅长
Since you're willing to take on some of
云雀姑娘既然愿意分忧
the burdens, I can only be happy.
那再好不过了
My Lady.
夫人
Sir,
沈管家
please bring them
还麻烦你把账本拿过来
to Lady Yun Que.
交给云雀姑娘
I've been busy with official duties,
近日我有公务在身
so Lady Yun Que will make
内院中大小事务
all decisions on the household matters.
一律都由云雀姑娘定夺
Then,
云雀姑娘
we'll count on you.
辛苦你了
[My Lady,]
夫人
[please think it through.]
您要三思啊
[Mr Shen was just temporarily misled.]
郎君也是一时眼花
[That temptress must]
必然是被那个
[have used some tricks]
外边的狐狸精
to deceive him
使用鬼蜮伎俩
[into bringing her here.]
哄着带到家里来的
Don't worry.
您放心
There's only one first lady
在他心里第一夫人
[in his heart.]
只有一位
[All of us are also]
另外我们大伙
on your side.
也站在您这边啊
Sir,
沈老管家
it really has nothing to do
真的跟云雀姑娘
with Yun Que.
没有关系
My Lady,
夫人
please don't take me as a fool.
您别把老奴当成糊涂
If you're not angry at her,
要不是被那狐狸精气到
why would you
您何至于
move back to your family home?
搬回娘家去住啊
Family home? No!
谁说我要回娘家住了
I'm busy with the investigation
我这几日查案事务多
and probably need to stay up late
恐怕要在刑部
at the Ministry of Justice.
熬到挺晚的
So I won't be living here for a while.
我就先不回来住了
Don't worry.
您别管我了
I should go now.
走了
How... can this be? Truly.
这 这如何是好啊 这个
Cut to the chase.
有话就说
Sir,
大阁领
when you're these days,
您不在府的这些日子里
Lady Yun Que
云雀姑娘
kept messing around
她天天换这个瓷盘
with the servants at home.
换那个绣布的
Chamberlain Shen can't bear her anymore.
忠叔天天和她对呛
He even gave me an ultimatum today,
今日还给我下了死命令
saying that if I failed to
说如果我再不把
bring you and Her Lady back,
您和夫人带回来
I wouldn't be allowed to go back.
就不许我回府了
When did he
忠大管家
become so close to Yan Xing?
几时和颜六娘这么好了
Sir,
大阁领
could you please clarify things for me?
您能否给属下一个明示
At first, I thought you
一开始我以为您是
liked Lady Yun Que.
心悦云雀姑娘
But ever since
可自从
you brought her back to the residence,
您把她带回府之后
you've never gone back there.
您就再也没回过府
So,
这我
which side should I be on?
我该站哪边
Looks like you have a lot of free time.
景内卫公务很清闲啊
You have the time to worry about
竟然开始操心起
my family affairs?
我沈某的内务了
I'm sorry.
卑职错了
Get up.
起来吧
How is the security setup
几日后的安防
for the next few days?
布置得如何了
My Lord,
回大阁领的话
it's all ready.
都好了
The security for the Secretary's
麟台秘书省的安防
Office has now been
现在已经完全由
fully taken over by the IG.
我们内卫府来接管
[The former guards]
原来的护卫
[have been reassigned to aid]
已经调去支援
[the Delinquents at the Imperial Academy.]
弘文馆异良人那边了
Jiang Langxing is over there.
江郎行在那儿
Perfect.
那正好
Let's finish this quickly and go home.
我们赶紧说完就回家
Jiang Langxing.
江郎行
[Candidates must not talk to each other.]
考生之间不得彼此交谈
Mr Xu asked us to bring you a message.
徐帅让我们给你传个信
Listen carefully.
你听好了
The latest directives from above
上头最新指示
stress again the importance of this exam.
再三强调事关重大
[It must be secured so thoroughly]
此次招考要封得
[that nothing can get in or out,]
连一只苍蝇都飞不出去
not even a fly.
一页书也带不进去
Did you get it?
听懂了吗
You... You spoke too fast.
你 你说太快了
I didn't get everything.
我没听清楚
Chuichui,
垂垂 垂垂
slow down a bit.
你稍微说得慢一点
Plus,
而且
hasn't Mr Xu instructed us
徐帅不也嘱咐我们了吗
to inspect more carefully
想让我们多看察一下
to ensure that
看看安防
there are no security oversights?
有没有疏漏的地方
We also need to inspect?
还要看察一下
Sorry,
两位
but how about coming with me inside?
要不随我进去看看
We've set up checkpoints
里面几道门
at various doors and courtyards.
内院我们也设了关卡
Chuichui,
垂垂
why don't the two of you go in first?
要不你们两个先进去吧
I'll wait for
我在这儿等等我五哥
my brother here.
看看他什么时候过来
That's right.
对哦
He passed the preliminary test as well.
你五哥也过了初试
Alright.
好吧
- Go ahead. - Then I'll go in then.
去吧去吧 那我进去了
Jiang Langxing,
江古板
let's go.
快点
[It's not easy being a matchmaker.]
月老不好当啊
Excuse me,
劳烦
could you
请问
help me find someone?
您能帮我找一个人吗
Pan Chi.
潘驰
[The man you are looking for]
你找的这个人
is indeed on the list for the final exam.
他确实是在终试名单上
[But until now, he still]
但是到现在
[hasn't registered for the exam yet.]
还未登记应考呢
Chi,
阿潘
did you really give up?
你真的放弃了吗
[Who said I gave up?]
谁说我放弃了
Chi!
阿潘
It's really you!
真的是你
You came to the exam!
你来考了
That day,
那天啊
after I sobered up,
我酒醒之后
I thought about what you said to me.
想了想你跟我说的话
Finally the Imperial Academy
难得弘文馆
is open to all,
向所有人招录
with my incredible talent,
我这满腹才华
I must impress
必须得惊艳一下
those antiquated scholars
那帮腐朽的老夫子
and show them
让他们见识一下
what a truly great piece of writing is.
什么才是绝世的好文章
Congratulations.
恭喜恭喜
Then I wish you great success
那就祝你一举高中
and get into the Imperial Academy.
榜上有名
Since you are named Pan Chi,
你既然也叫潘驰
like the renowned detective,
和民间第一神探同名
you must be just as talented.
必是一样的优秀
Today,
今日一看
you look particularly radiant.
更是容光焕发
Of course.
那是自然
With just a little effort,
我这随便捯饬一番
I will surely be captivating,
必定是英俊潇洒
the most dashing in Xiang'an.
艳绝襄安
But jokes aside,
这玩笑归玩笑
you don't look too well.
你的脸色可不太好
Did you drink again these days?
这两天可是又醉酒了
These days I've been
我这几天
busy looking through records for the case,
忙着查案子看卷宗呢
but
但
I've got nothing.
毫无头绪
Is the case you're talking about
你说的案子
that case
不会是那什么
about the moth or something?
扑棱蛾子的案子吧
You know about it?
你知道
Of course I know about it.
自然是知道
The whole city knows about it.
全城都知道
It's becoming legendary.
传得神乎其神的
But I think,
不过依我看呀
you shouldn't only look at records.
你就别只查卷宗了
You need to ask around some more.
你得多去问问人
I've asked everyone involved.
周边的人我都问过了
One of them
当事人
died,
一个死了
the other one went mad.
一个疯了
So what?
那又怎样
In our line of work,
干我们这行的
we're least afraid of dealing with bodies.
最不惧怕尸体
The bodies
这死人身上
can tell you a lot of things.
好东西可多着呢
Plus,
再说了
even a madman's words
这疯子说的话
are not all necessarily nonsense.
也不一定说的全是疯话
[This is]
这笔锋
[Father's writing before he got hurt.]
是父亲受伤前的笔迹
[When Lord Shen was young,]
沈大人年轻之时
his writing was as sharp
笔锋如剑
and vigorous as a sword.
遒劲恢弘
But later on,
这后来呢
his writing became
却是
more refined,
笔锋藏拙
more classic and smooth.
古朴圆润
[It took me a long time]
老朽也是练了许久
[to be able to]
才能做到
[write just like he did.]
笔迹如出一辙呀
[So it was forged.]
果然是伪造的
[But if it was Erudite Yan, who knew]
若真是了解父亲书法的
[Father's writing well, that framed him,]
颜博士陷害
[he wouldn't have]
必然不会使用
[used the wrong brush technique.]
错误的笔锋
[Someone else]
伪造之人
[must have forged it.]
另有其人
Chi,
阿潘
thank you.
谢谢你
Your suggestion has helped
经过你的提醒
me come up with a different approach.
我似乎想到了别的办法
Me?
我
I didn't give you any suggestions.
我可没提醒你
C'mon, there you are, my darling.
夫人让我好找啊
Why aren't you at the Ministry of Justice
不在刑部议事
but chatting here?
怎么跑这儿来闲聊了
Sir,
大阁领
I'm here on official business.
我来此是有公务在身
You only need to focus on
你管好你内卫府
the IG's affairs.
分内的事就行
My whereabouts everyday
我每天干什么去哪里
is none of your business.
轮不到你插手
I don't care about your business.
刑部的事情我管不着
But what if it's about
但如果是
your family duties?
夫人的分内之事呢
The house is in chaos.
后宅乱作一团
As my wife,
你作为大阁领夫人
you should go back and handle it.
理当回去管管了
Let's go back.
回府
Are you dreaming of
你是不是妄想
being on equal footing with Her Lady
和夫人平起平坐
and serving the same husband?
共事一夫啊
[Let me tell you,]
我告诉你
as long as I'm still alive,
只要我还活着
don't even think about marrying into.
你就别想进沈家这门
That's not up to you.
这可由不得你
Listen,
我再说一次
give me the accounts.
把账本给我
Greetings, Mr and Mrs Shen.
大阁领 夫人
My Lord,
郎君
you brought Her Lady back.
把夫人接回来了
[As the saying goes,]
这古话说得好
[couples that argue but then make up]
夫妻床头打架床尾合
will stay together for life.
这才能白头偕老呢
Sir,
沈管家
I'm a bit hungry.
我有点饿了
Could you check
您要不去厨房
the dinner?
看一下今天的菜
Okay.
好嘞
Right away.
马上去
Lady Yun Que,
云雀姑娘
stop arguing with Chamberlain Shen.
你别跟老管家吵了
Don't worry.
你不用担心
On our first day of marriage,
从我成婚第一天起
we agreed to divorce
就跟大阁领约好了
in the future.
日后和离
Sooner or later,
这账本
you'll be in charge of the accounts.
早晚是你管
Divorce?
和离
A good man like Mr Shen,
大阁领这么好的男人
why don't you cherish him?
夫人还不珍惜
[He's exceptionally talented]
大阁领一表人才
[and strikingly good-looking.]
玉树临风
[Whoever can't see that]
谁若是看不到这一点
must be blind.
谁才是真的有眼无珠呢
It's a pity that such a good girl
多好的一个姑娘
doesn't have good eyesight.
可惜眼睛不好使
[What are you laughing at?]
你笑什么
Is it that
难不成
you think Mr Shen is ugly?
你觉得大阁领很丑
No, no, no.
不是不是不是
Lady Yun Que,
云雀姑娘
one ought to think
饭可以乱吃
before talking.
话可不能乱说
I don't think we're
我看这儿已经没有
needed here.
我们什么事了
Let's leave soon.
还是赶紧离开为好
Don't drag me.
你别拉我
Then walk yourself.
那你自己走
Come live here again.
回府住吧
After all,
毕竟
we...
我们
I know.
我明白
[I'm not the one you want.]
我不是你心里那个人
If others find out,
若是被外人知道
it will only result in more rumors.
徒增口舌
After the case is closed,
等忙完案子
I will move back.
我会回来的
I won't get you into trouble.
不会给你添麻烦
[The Great Grandmother]
太皇太后
[has picked the final exam topic.]
今日抽中终试试题
[We open it by her order.]
我等奉旨拆开
[The topic is]
题为
[to immerse in the grand scenery]
赏雁归霁色
[and thriving Xiang'an.]
观襄安盛景
[No restrictions on literary form.]
文材不限
[Poetry and essays are preferred.]
诗赋尤佳
Remove him.
带走
Your Highness,
禀太皇太后
we've reviewed the papers for 3 days
臣等阅卷三日
and finalized the list of candidates
已定下弘文馆
[for admission to the Imperial Academy.]
最终招录的名录
[Please review the list.]
请太皇太后审阅
The papers are placed by score.
考卷已按评分名次摆好
[The first]
上面第一篇
[is from Cheng Bojian,]
就是本次第一名
[this year's top scorer.]
程伯简的文章
[So Pan Chi]
这潘驰
got the last place.
就是最后一名
Yes.
正是
Wan,
婉儿
read the last-placed essay
你把这最后一名的
[to me.]
给哀家读读
Tall pines at the foot of the mountain,
高松植山脚
[short saplings at the summit.]
矮苗生峰顶
[That's why even the short saplings]
以苗径寸茎
can overshadow the hundred-foot pines.
遮松百尺条
In my opinion,
哀家觉得
the last-placed one shows
这最后一名的文采
impressive literary skill.
也是斐然啊
Pan Chi's work
这潘驰
didn't fall short in literary talent,
倒不是输在文采上
[but]
而是
was somewhat off-topic.
有些偏题
I don't really understand
这些哀家倒是有些
what you meant.
听不懂了
Wan,
婉儿
why don't you explain it to me?
你就给哀家解读解读
He compares the tall pine trees
此考生是以雁归山脚
at the foot of mountains
高大的松树
to the scholars with humble backgrounds,
喻指寒门才子
[and the short saplings on the top]
以山顶低矮的小苗
[as the sons of noble families.]
喻指世家子弟
[Because of high-born status,]
因生来地势就高
even the short saplings
径寸之苗
can still overshadow the tallest pines.
却能遮盖百尺之松
I think
我看
the description of the scenery
这雁归山的景
is quite amazing.
描写得很妙啊
Go on.
接着念
I laugh loudly toward the sky.
仰天大笑去
[Striding across the divine realm.]
高步踏神州
[The noble may think themselves noble,]
贵者虽自贵
[but I see them as mere dust.]
吾视若尘埃
[The humble may think themselves lowly,]
贱者虽自贱
[who says they don't carry great weight?]
谁言不千钧
[I gaze at the mountains]
振衣览群山
[and dip my feet into the long river.]
濯足于长河
[Not only will I take the exam,]
潘驰我不仅要考
I'll also expose
还要撕下
your hideous face!
你们丑恶的面皮
I can tell your mind
我看你这心思
isn't on the chessboard at all.
根本没在棋盘上
Do you want to ask me why,
你是不是想问哀家呀
[though I saw the corruption in]
为何明明看出了
the Imperial Academy's selection process,
弘文馆选拔有腌臜行径
I still approved
为什么
the original list?
还通过了原定名单
I did want to ask you.
臣原本确实想问
But then I understood.
但刚才已经想明白了
Though Pan Chi is brilliant in literary,
这个潘驰虽文采斐然
he is too impulsive.
但个性太冲动
So,
所以
he's not suitable to be a court official.
本就不适合为官入仕
This exam
这次考试
was just an experiment.
本就是试水之举
[The selection process]
才子选拔
[has long been corrupted.]
积弊已久
Many court officials
朝中官员
were involved.
有许多牵涉其中
It has become a well-defended
已经是固若金汤
stalemate.
一盘死局了
Even if I want to make a move in this game,
我纵然想动这盘棋
I have to
也得看看
find the right time to place my piece.
合适的落子时机
[I gaze at the mountains]
振衣览群山
[and dip my feet into the long river.]
濯足于长河
What grand and magnificent writing!
此文写得大气磅礴呀
It uses scenery to mock current affairs,
借景讽今
implying that someone
暗示有人
under the guise of
借不拘门第
fair selection
公平选拔之名
are suppressing the commoners
行打压寒门
to solidify the power of noble families.
固化门阀之实
How gratifying!
好不痛快
Okay now.
行了
You've been praising this friend of yours
你都夸你这好友
non-stop.
夸半天了
But he does write very well.
那人家确实写得很好嘛
Chi
阿潘
shares
不只是
a name with the greatest detective.
与民间第一神探同名
He may be
他还很可能
the detective himself.
就是神探本人
It's almost certain.
八九不离十了
Ms Yan.
颜书吏
Mr Xu asked me to tell you
徐帅托我告诉你
[that he's got a lead on]
你让他帮忙调查
[Chen Shoujie's background report]
陈守杰履历一事
[that you're interested in.]
有眉目了
Chen Shoujie was indeed
陈守杰他确实
involved in Chen Huo'e case
参与了侦办陈火蛾一案
[and was even promoted for it.]
而且还因此获得了晋升
Only that, he went mad
只不过晋升之后不久
shortly after his promotion.
他便疯了
So he already went mad
原来陈夫人死之前
before Mrs Chen died.
他就已经疯了
We must have missed something
火蛾案跟他
between him
一定还有勾连
and the fire moth case.
是我们没有发现的
Looks like
不行
I need to go to the Chen residence again.
我得再去一趟陈府
Shen Du.
沈渡
Are you okay?
没事吧
Watch out!
小心
[The form is different from that day,]
暗器形制虽与那日不同
[the way the hidden weapon was used is]
可射出的招式
[remarkably similar.]
却极为相似
You're hurt.
你受伤了
It's nothing.
无妨
Just a small cut.
小伤
Why did you come here alone?
你怎么会一个人来这儿
I came to find someone but he's not here.
我来找人没找着
You're bleeding a lot.
你流这么多血
How can you be fine?
怎么可能没事呢
Are you worried about me?
你是在关心我吗
I'm not worried about you.
我才没有关心你
You got hurt because you were saving me.
你是为了救我才受伤的
I need to be responsible for you.
我总该对你负责吧
Father must be really out of it.
这老爹可真是糊涂了
The shop is closed.
店铺明明关得好好的
Yet he insisted that I go check
还非要我过去
if there's been any thefts.
检查有没有失窃
Where do you think you're going?
你还想跑
I advise you not to make more mistakes.
我劝你不要一错再错
I'm a clerk at the Ministry of Justice.
我可是刑部女官
If you turn yourself in,
你若是自行告罪
you may get a lighter sentence for theft.
盗窃之罪或可轻判
But if you hurt me,
可你若是伤了我
that would be a serious offense.
那可是重罪
You meddlesome woman.
多管闲事的婆娘
Die!
去死吧
Help!
救命啊
It's you.
是你啊
[Who's there?]
什么人
Wait.
不是
Wait a second.
你等会儿
It were
刚才
the Delinquents
那巡逻的
who were patrolling.
是异良人
Why do we need to hide?
我们为什么要躲啊
I...
我
Don't want to deal with the officials.
不想与公门中人打交道
You avoid
你忌讳
dealing with the officials,
与公门中人打交道
and you are skilled in martial arts.
又武艺高强
I know who you are.
我知道你的身份了
You must be
你是
a vigilante hero against injustice, right?
路见不平的江湖英雄吧
You put on the mask at night
夜晚戴上面具
and become a warrior for justice.
化身秉公义士
[You uphold justice and]
行侠仗义
do good deeds without seeking recognition.
做好事不留名那种
Kind of.
算是吧
Wait.
等一下
You can't leave.
你不能走
You killed someone.
你杀了人
What?
怎么
Are you arresting me?
你要抓我报官
I killed the man who wanted to kill you.
我杀的可是杀你的人
This is how you treat
你就是这般对待
your savior?
救命恩人的
According to our laws,
论大苍律法
anyone who kills the perpetrator
夜晚无故行凶杀人
facing unjustified night violence
反抗殴击行凶者至死
won't be held accountable.
便可不论刑责
But,
可是
you can't
你也不能
just leave like this.
这么一走了之啊
What are you doing?
你这是做什么
To release a water lantern for you.
帮你放水灯呀
When I was little,
小时候
my mother often
我阿娘
brought me here to release water lanterns.
就常带我来放水灯
[My mother said]
阿娘说
that water lanterns can float away,
水灯能够随波逐流而去
carrying away misfortunes and illnesses,
可以消灾消病
and can
还能够
[take away]
把身上不好的东西
all bad things.
都给祛除掉
Even though you killed to protect me,
虽然你是为了救我
it's still better
可还是
to release a water lantern
帮你放个水灯
to clear away any bad karma from killing.
消除一下杀业比较好
No need.
不必了
I don't believe in these things.
我不信这些
If you believe it, then it will work.
信则有 信则灵
I didn't believe it as a kid either.
小时候我也不信
So I was always half-hearted doing it.
所以放得十分敷衍
And then,
后来
my mother grew sicker and sicker
我阿娘病得越来越重
and eventually left me.
离开了我
I often wonder,
我常常在想
if back then,
如果那个时候
I had released every
我能够认认真真地
every water lantern sincerely,
去放每一盏水灯
would the heavens
是不是老天爷
make my wish come true
就会遂了我的心愿
and let my mother always be here with me.
让阿娘一直陪伴着我
Even if you release 1000 water lanterns,
就算放千只万只水灯
people would still leave.
该走的人也还是会走
In this life,
今生今世
they've already decided that
她们早已打定主意
they would stay with us only this long.
只肯陪我们走这一程
You can't change that.
改变不了
You can't change nothing at all.
一切都改变不了
Ghostface.
鬼面
My Lord,
大阁领
the thief hanged himself in the alley.
那匪徒在深巷自缢
We can't find out who he was.
查不出身份
He hanged himself?
自缢而亡
If they wanted to kill him,
既然要灭口
of course they won't let us
就不会想让我们
find out who he was.
查出身份的
You're dismissed.
下去吧
Yes.
是
Sir,
大阁领
do you really not need a doctor
真的不用叫大夫来瞧瞧
[or some medication?]
不用上药
Mind your own business.
多嘴
No need.
不必
[Who said there's no need?]
谁说不必了
I'll apply some medication for you.
上药
Do you have other things to do later?
一会儿还有别的事吗
You seem so rushed.
我看你神色匆忙
It can't be that you're off to rest, right?
总不能是赶着去休息吧
Of course not.
那当然不是了
I was thinking,
我是想着
if after treating you
若是给你上完药
it's still not too late,
不算太晚的话
I can go to the Ministry of Justice
我还可以去刑部
and organize the case details.
整理一下案情
The case is this pressing that
案子这么紧
you can't rest even at night?
半夜都不能休息
I was just hoping to
那我不是想着
solve it sooner.
早点破案嘛
Staying up is nothing.
熬一夜也没什么
But I'm hurt.
但是我受伤了
Can't you stay here
难道今晚
and take care of me tonight?
不能留下来照顾我吗
I... I...
我 我
Forget it.
算了
I don't need you to take care of me.
不用你照顾
Go ahead.
忙去吧
Let me do it.
我来我来
Who said I was leaving?
谁说我要走了
You got hurt because you were saving me.
你是因为救我才受伤的
If I leave now,
我若是现在走了
the heavens would think
那老天爷都会觉得
I have no conscience.
我没有良心
And what if it
那万一到时候
sends a lightning to strike me,
一道雷劈下来
wouldn't I be wrongly punished?
那我不是冤枉 我
You must have pulled on my wound.
应该是扯到伤口了
Don't get distracted.
别分神
Treat the wound well.
帮我好好包
Sure, sure.
好好好
Perhaps
可能刚刚
I didn't bandage it well earlier.
是我包扎得不够好
Now it's better.
现在好了
It's getting late.
时候不早了
You should get some rest.
你早点休息吧
My Lord.
主上
My Lord, please spare my life.
主上饶命
I have found out that
属下已探听到
the Delinquents are treating this
异良人那边
as a typical case of thieves fighting
已按寻常盗贼互殴案
among themselves and didn't
处理
report it to the Ministry of Justice.
都未报到刑部
Useless!
废物
Send someone more competent next time.
派利索点的人去办事
If it goes wrong again,
若再失误
you'll be the next one to die.
下一个死的就是你
[I've learnt my lesson.]
属下知错
Thank you for sparing my life.
谢主上不杀之恩
Lu Chuichui at the Ministry of Justice.
刑部的那个陆垂垂
No one touches her.
谁都不许动她
Yes.
是
You're dismissed.
下去吧
[A bunch of ignorant fools.]
这帮愚昧无知的草包
[A simple fire moth trick]
区区一个火蛾戏法
[can cause such chaos.]
便可搅得天翻地覆
[Before long,]
用不了多久
[the empire...]
这大苍
You should get up now.
你先起来吧
Go eat something in the front hall.
去前厅吃点东西
People need to eat more
人受了伤
when they're hurt.
就更要多吃点了
You saw it yourself.
你也看到了
I'm badly hurt.
我现在身受重伤
[I can't move.]
行动不便
It's too hard to go to the front hall.
去前厅太麻烦了
I only want to lie down.
我只想躺着
Fine.
好吧
Then get some rest.
那你好好休息
I'll
我待会儿
bring you some breakfast later.
去把早食给你端过来
What?
不是
Where's Yan Xing?
夫人呢
She's invited
颜府来人
by the Yans to a banquet.
请夫人赴宴去了
[She instructed that you're badly hurt]
她交代大阁领您伤重
[and don't need to go there with her.]
不必与她一起赴宴
I...
我
[She asked us to serve you food.]
要我们好好伺候您吃饭
You're dismissed.
下去吧
Yes.
是
Sir, I...
大阁领 我
What?
什么事
I found it.
我查到了
Han Shiyuan
那个韩世元
is not what he seems.
可不简单
Xing,
六娘
Shiyuan and I
我和韩郎
are engaged to be married next month.
已定于下月成亲
I'll use tea as wine
我以茶代酒
to toast to you and Shiyuan and
敬三姐和韩郎君一杯
wish you a lifetime of happiness together.
祝你们百年好合
I ask for your forgiveness
此前我有急躁
if I had been
礼数不周的地方
rude and inconsiderate before.
还请你们原谅
[No need, no need.]
言重了言重了
Okay then.
好了好了
Sit down first and talk.
快坐下说吧
Our family has been blessed with
我们颜府今年啊
a series of joyful events this year.
真是喜事连连
Mojie got into the Imperial Academy,
墨杰考入了弘文馆
Xing and Caiwei
六娘和采薇啊
[both married well.]
都找到了好的归宿
Xing,
六娘
why did you often come back here recently?
你最近怎么老回娘家呀
Did you have a fight
是不是跟大阁领
with your husband?
闹不愉快了
No, no.
没有没有
I'm doing well there.
我在沈府挺好的
But a few days ago,
就是前几日吧
the cook
那个厨娘
has taken a few days off to go home.
请假回家了几日
[So I couldn't eat well there.]
饭菜有些不合胃口
I'm just here for the food.
我这不回家来吃饭嘛
That's good then.
那没事就好
The rumors say that
外面传言啊
as soon as you're back home,
说你只要一回娘家
Chief Shen would come here to take you.
大阁领就来绑人
This situation
这状态吧
[is indeed a bit terrifying.]
是有点吓人
[When you came back last time]
可你上次回娘家
[and he didn't come to take you,]
他没来绑人
I was feeling even more uneasy.
我反倒觉得不安心了
My Lord, My Lady,
老爷 夫人
Chief Shen is here.
大阁领来了
Greetings.
大阁领
Please take a seat.
大阁领 请上座
Weren't you having difficulty moving?
夫君不是行动不便吗
I can't miss my father-in-law's
岳父家宴
family banquet.
不可不来
That's right.
是啊是啊
This way,
大阁领
please.
里边请 里边请